Guide to the Monterey Jazz Festival Collection ARS.0018
Archive of Recorded Sound
- Non-Festival recordings, circa 1955-1979; 37 audiotape reel(s)
  - Excerpts from Concert by the Sea - Erroll Garner, 1955 September 19; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 4)
    Side two features interviews with Erroll Garner, Denzil Best, and Eddie Calhoun.
    Garner, Erroll; Calhoun, Eddie; Best, Denzil
  - Andre Previn at Sunset Auditorium, circa 1958; 2 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, half track, 7.5 ips] (Box 107, Reel 5B, Reel 5A)
    Untitled; Untitled; A hundred years from today; Sometimes I'm happy; Angel eyes; Bernie's tune; Untitled; My funny valentine; Lets get away from it all; three formal pieces (Previn, solo piano).
    Bennett, Betty; André Previn Trio
  - Reseda and Burbank High School Bands, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 6)
    A note accompanying this reel mentions that this recording is from a High School band competition for Monterey Jazz Festival. The date and location however are unknown, as is the set list.
  - High School Winning Band and Combo 1974, 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 7)
    Tracklisting (Grant Union)
    Valencia; Parker's mood and Moody's mood; Naiesha; Bag's groove
    Tracklisting (Eagle Rock)
    Caissons go rolling along; Untitled; Untitled; Untitled; Bluegatta.
    Eagle Rock High School Band; Grant Union High School Combo
  - Stu Williamson, 1960; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 8)
    Appears to be a studio produced demo tape.
    Cool Breeze; Hungary Child; Rosebud.
    Jazz inc; Williamson, Stu
  - John Lewis, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 7.5 ips, mono] (Box 107, Reel 9)
    Lyon head; Mirjana of my soul; Beach head; Mirjana of my heart.
    Date and location of recording unknown
    Lewis, John
  - Blood, Sweat, and Tears, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, quarter track, 7.5 ips] (Box 107, Reel 10)
    Applause; Yesterday's music (Someone belongs to everyone); Naked man (Beware of the naked man); Got to get you into my life; Takin it home.
    Appears to be a studio session, possibly captured (according to a note on the reel's container) at: "Record Plant Studios, 321 West 44th Street, New York, NY, 10036".
    Date of session is unknown.
    Blood, Sweat, and Tears (Musical group); Clayton-Thomas, David
  - Jimmy Lyons: Crosstalk, with Jon Faddis and Dizzy Gillespie, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 3.75 ips] (Box 107, Reel 11)
    Jimmy Lyons interviews trumpeters Jon Faddis and Dizzy Gillespie for the radio program Crosstalk, broadcast on KEST (San Francisco).
    Date of broadcast unknown.
    Faddis, Jon; Gillespie, Dizzy; Lyons, Jimmy; KEST 1450 AM
  - Jimmy Lyons Radio Show, 1975 April 12; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 3.75 ips] (Box 107, Reel 12)
    A radio show by Jimmy Lyons, broadcast on KEST (San Francisco). Mr Lyons explains at the start of the broadcast that his show airs on Saturday evenings between 8-10pm. Includes tunes by Woody Herman (Hitch Hike On The Possum Trot Line), Duke Ellington (Love you madly), Chuck Mangione Quartet (Legend of the one-eyed sailor), Carmen McRae (Spring Can Really Hang You Up the Most), Oscar Peterson (Easy listening blues), John Coltrane (Naima), and Wes Montgomery (West coast blues).
    KEST 1450 AM; Lyons, Jimmy
  - Heritage Jazz Festival 1977: Ella Fitzgerald with The Tommy Flanagan Trio, 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 108, Reel 13)
    Too close for comfort; Ain't got nothing but the blues; Satin doll; I never knew; Feelings; One note samba; Ordinary dream; Mr. Pagganini; You are the sunshine of my life.
    Also included are three spot announcements for the National Public Radio broadcast of the above.
    Wonder, Stevie; Tommy Flanagan Trio; Fitzgerald, Ella; National Public Radio (U.S.)
  - Montreux Jazz Festival - I, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 108, Reel 14)
    Eddie "Lockjaw" Davis Quartet with Ray Brown, Oscar Peterson, and Jimmy Smith: Blue Lou.
    Dave Brubeck Quartet with Darius, Christopher and Daniel Brubeck: [no setlist].
    Joe Venuti: Autumn lesson and a violin lesson progression.
    National Public Radio (U.S.); Venuti, Joe; Eddie Lockjaw Davis Quartet; Dave Brubeck Quartet
  - Montreux Jazz Festival - II, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 108, Reel 15)
    Sweet Georgia brown; The nearness of you; Hum scat with the bass; Improvisation on all blue; there will never be another you; You ain't gonna bother me no more; Stella by starlight; Roll' em Pete.
    Also included: Jazz Alive - two spot announcements for the above.
    Dawson, Alan; Cobb, Arnett; National Public Radio (U.S.); Larkins, Ellis; Holley, Major; Williams, Joe; Mitchell, Billy
  - Heritage Jazz Festival 1977: Al Belletto Septet; Roy Eldridge and the Tommy Flanagan Trio, 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 108, Reel 16)
    Al Belleto Septet: Falling in love with love; No.64; Basically Blues. Roy Eldridge and the Tommy Flanagan Trio: Sometimes I'm happy; St.James infirmary; Let me off uptown. Interview with Tommy Flanagan.
    Al Belletto Septet; Tommy Flanagan Trio; Flanagan, Tommy; National Public Radio (U.S.); Eldridge, Roy
  - Sergio Mendes: Brazil 65 and 66, circa 1965-1966; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 17)
    Brazil 65: So nice; Favela; Berimban; Tristeya em mim; Aquarius; One note samba; So nice; Ninto a vontade; Let me; Consola cao; Reza. Brazil 66: Mas que nada; One note samba; Spanish flea; The joker; Going out of my head; Tim dom dom; Day tripper; Aqua de beber; Slow hot wind; O pato; Berimban.
    Mendes, Sergio
  - Bob Dorough at Concerts by the Sea, with Bill Takus., 1976 April; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 18)
    Simon Smith and his dancing bear; Better than anything; I'm beginning to see the light; A hundred years from today; I'm hip; Nothing like you; Small day tomorrow; Norwegian wood; Just because were kids; Just about everything.
    Includes a handwritten note to '"Jimmy'"(presumably Jimmy Lyons), dated "9 June", in which David Smith writes that this reel is a cut from a new album by Bob Dorough, that he (Smith) helped produce. Smith suggests that Dorough "would be a great addition to this years festival".
    Takus, Bill; Smith, Dennis; Dorough, Bob
  - An American Concerto, 1976 May 26; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, quarter track, 7.5 ips, stereo] (Box 107, Reel 19)
    Williams, Patrick
  - Berkeley High School Jazz Quintet, Reno 78, 1978; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 20)
    Hardyman, Phil
  - Radio broadcast, KOCN-FM, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 21)
    Poorly spliced mixture of different tunes.
    Reel appears to have been auditioned. Tunes highlighted: Just friends (Marmarosso, piano; Thompson, Marshall, drums; Jones, Sam, bass); Cold Duck Time (Harris, Eddie); Queen Mother stomp (Ray Brown Big Band); The kid (Ousley, Harold); Come back Charleston blue (Jones, Quincy; Hathaway, Donna); Hearse to the graveyard
    KOCN-FM
  - Festival suite: in memoriam. Premiere., 1976 April 2; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, quarter track, 3.75 ips, stereo] (Box 107, Reel 22)
    Includes a note from Clausen, Alf to Lyons, Jimmy that outlines that the recording is a "good tape of Fri. afternoon's premiere of my Festival Suite. This should present it in a little better light. Let me know what you decide and if you need anything else".
    Orange Coast College Jazz Ensemble; Mitchell, Blue; Spencer, Dick (Trumpet player); Clausen, Alf; Clausen, Alf
  - Jimmy Lyons at Cerritos, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 23)
    Includes a note that reads "Cerritos broadcast. No music".
    Lyons, Jimmy
  - Disco #2, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 7.5 ips] (Box 107, Reel 24)
  - Disco #3, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 7.5 ips] (Box 107, Reel 25)
  - Disco #4, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 7.5 ips] (Box 107, Reel 26)
  - Kanin Knog / Bengt Hallberg, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 7.5 ips, CCIR, stereo] (Box 107, Reel 27)
    It ain't nobody's business; I was doing all right; I'm singing this song to you.
    Hallberg,, Bengt
  - Ted Curson, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 3.75 ips, 2 track] (Box 107, Reel 28)
    Scope and Contents
    The Jazz Set (PBS), 1972: Typical Ted; The leopard; Reeva's waltz. Ode to Booker Ervin (LP): Airi's tune, LSD takes a holiday. Flip flop (LP). Reeva's waltz (live at U.C. Berkeley, 1972 April). Still life.
    Curson, Ted
  - Untitled, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 29)
    General note
    Scotch 140, tartan series tape. Contents unknown.
  - Concert Jazz for Stage Bands, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, 4" open reel tape] (Box 107, Reel 30)
    Demo tape of arrangement and original compositions by Richmond, Kim, designed for college stage bands. Tape container includes accompanying cover letter and tracklisting.
    Real George (CJ-208); Sister Sadie (CJ-110); Gems (CJ-309); Indian summer (CJ-109); City of LA (CJ-406); Days of wine and roses (CJ-305); Then came Bronson (CJ-205); Mini tiger (CJ-210); Sojourn (CJ-111); In a mellowtone (CJ-108); Nice (CJ-307); Under the loop (CJ-209); You'll never know (CJ-211); Yesterday (CJ-308); Mayo (CJ-212).
    Richmond, Kim; Richmond, Kim
  - Nine Piece Band Dubs, 1961 December 19; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape. 15 ips] (Box 107, Reel 31)
    Going going gone; Song for Carl; Green Dolphin; Contiki.
    Recording venue
    Recorded at United Recording.
  - KJAZ, 1960 June 28; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 32)
    Contents unknown.
  - Mood Music - Personal Property - Lyons, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 33)
  - Untitled, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 107, Reel 34)
  - When Jeremiah Sang the Blues, 1974 August 6; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape, quarter track, 7.5 ips, stereo] (Box 107, Reel 35)
  - Skelton - Tape 1 - Set 1, undated; 1 audiotape reel(s) [Quarter inch tape] (Box 108, Reel 36)
- Documentation, circa 1958-2013; 13 box(es)
  - Ephemera, circa 1995-2008; 1 box(es) [2 folders and 1 QIC data tape] (Box 111)
    Limited edition commemorative stamps, assorted advertising materials, and information documenting ticket sales from 1994.
  - Board minutes and financial records. Archive formation., 1958-1983; 1 box(es) [14 folders, 1 book] (Box 112)
    Board meeting minutes 1958-1968. Balance sheets and income statements 1958-1980. Archive records circa 1980-1983.
  - Programs, 1958-2013; 5 box(es) (Box 114, Box 113, Box 115, Box 123, Box 124)
    Arrangement
    1958-1995 (Box 113). 1996- (Box 114).
    Duplicates
    Boxes 115, 123 and 124 contains duplicate copies of programs found in boxes 113 and 114
  - Container materials and annotated program copies., circa 1958-2005; 1 box(es) [9 folders] (Box 116)
    Photocopied and original paper based materials found inside sound recording containers for item numbers MJF0001-MJF1072. Photocopies of programs with annotations for festivals between 1958-2005. Photocopies of discarded tape boxes.
  - Monterey Jazz Festival - Archive of Recorded Sound correspondence. Collection loans and requests., circa 1990-2012; 1 box(es) [21 folders] (Box 117)
    Correspondence between the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound and the Monterey Jazz Festival between 1990-2012. Also included are documents related to Monterey Jazz Festival Collection's formation, access conditions, duplication, circulation, and early arrangement work.
  - Media content documentation, 1958-2005; 1 box(es) [11 folders] (Box 118)
    Recording engineer notes for a number of live recordings in the collection between 1958-2005. These notes tend to include a rundown/set list with timings for each performance.
  - Collection processing and NHPRC grant documentation, circa 2004-2011; 1 box(es) [5 folders] (Box 119)
    Barcodes and various inventories. Contents of videos 1650s. Inserts from duplicate cassettes. NHPRC, letters of support, originals. NHPRC, grant documentation.
  - Performer index cards 1958-1978, 2 box(es) (Box 120, Box 121)
    Index of performance dates by artist, between 1958-1978. Includes details of accompanying performers in each instance.
    A-Z by artist surname. Box 120, A-J. Box 121, K-Z.
- Photographs, 2008; 2 item(s)
  - Monterey Jazz Festival 50th Anniversary Tour., June-July 2008; 1 dvd-r(s) (Box 106)
    Photos of concerts at Purchase College, Purchase, NY (2008 June 3) and Tilles Center, Brookville, NY (2008 July 03).
    Gillis, Richard
  - MJF50 Allstars 2008 Tour jpegs, 1 optical disc(s) (cd-r) (Box 106)
    Michael Piazza Photography
- Books and periodicals, 1978-2007; 3 item(s)
  - Dizzy, Duke, The Count and Me: The Story of the Monterey Jazz Festival, 1978; 1 book(s); San Francisco Examiner. A California Living Book. ISBN 0-89395-005-X. Published 1978. (Box 109)
    Martin, David Stone; Lyons, Jimmy; Kamin, Ira
  - Monterey Jazz Festival: Forty Legendary Years, 1997; 1 book(s); Angel City Press. ISBN 1-883318-40-8. First published 1997. (Box 109)
    Minor, William; Wisher, Bill; Eastwood, Clint
  - Monterey Jazz Beat - Vol 6, Issues 1 and 2, 2007; 1 folder(s) [2 issues] (Box 109)